<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RStudio on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/rstudio/</link>
    <description>Recent content in RStudio on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/rstudio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Convert incorrect filled missing values to NA in R data frame</title>
      <link>/05/06/2020/conver-improper-filled-missing-values-to-na-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/06/2020/conver-improper-filled-missing-values-to-na-in-r/</guid>
      <description>One of the most important components of a data management strategy is the proper handling of missing values. Often you will find datasets that have used either zero or NA to represent missing values in cell of a data frame or table. The question that may sober our mind is that, which of the two way of storing missing value in the data is right? You will notice that everyone who deals with data has to deal with this important distinction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wordclouds plotting with ggwordcloud package in R</title>
      <link>/11/05/2019/wordclouds-plotting-with-ggwordcloud-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/05/2019/wordclouds-plotting-with-ggwordcloud-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, we saw how to make wordcloud graphic using the wordcloud package. In this post we extend the ability of R to make wordcloud graphic, but rather than using the base R function for plotting,I will show how to use ggplot2 framework.
Le Pennec and Slowikowski (2019) developed a gwordcloud package, which extend the capability of ggplot2 package (Wickham 2016) of making cloud text. With the geom_text_wordcloud() function, gwordcloud made making wordcloud plot easy with ggplot2 package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>publishing code into Technical Report</title>
      <link>/02/22/2019/publishing-code-into-technical-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/22/2019/publishing-code-into-technical-report/</guid>
      <description>You are creating a report based on some analysis you are doing in R. You are pasting code snippes and figures into your report document. The document is reviewed and you got comments and feedback of something went wrong in your report and you ought to redo it all over again.
The publishing tools in Rstudio allows you to run a script and automaticaly generate document containing the results, including images of each figures generated and imported; the code chunk and code blocks with text and mathematical equations that you insert and inserting references cited.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>