<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Convert incorrect filled missing values to NA in R data frame</title>
      <link>/05/06/2020/conver-improper-filled-missing-values-to-na-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/06/2020/conver-improper-filled-missing-values-to-na-in-r/</guid>
      <description>One of the most important components of a data management strategy is the proper handling of missing values. Often you will find datasets that have used either zero or NA to represent missing values in cell of a data frame or table. The question that may sober our mind is that, which of the two way of storing missing value in the data is right? You will notice that everyone who deals with data has to deal with this important distinction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographical coordinates conversion made easy with parzer package in R</title>
      <link>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Geographic coordinates are often in “degrees” but they can also include “minutes” and “seconds”. This gives us a variety of different formats for reporting the coordinates and you’ll see that different groups will use different formats. Computers do not really work well with DMS coordinates and we really prefer the coordinates to be in Decimal Degrees or DD.
This format allows us to perform standard decimal math operations on the coordinates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating wordcloud with wordcloud package in R</title>
      <link>/10/29/2019/creating-wordcloud-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/29/2019/creating-wordcloud-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Google describe a wordclous as an image composed of words used in a particular text or subject, in which the size of each word indicates its frequency or importance. The words that appear more often are also the ones stand as bigger and bolder in wordcloud graphic. You can create a word cloud, also referred as text cloud or tag cloud, which is a visual representation of text data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A glimpse of FAO&#39; fisheries statistics in R</title>
      <link>/10/16/2019/a-glimpse-of-fao-fisheries-statistics-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/16/2019/a-glimpse-of-fao-fisheries-statistics-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe OpenFisheries.org project created an open web platform aimed to advance the practice of data science in fisheries. The project has managed to consolidate global fisheries dataset that can be accessed and retrieved using modern analytics. The OpenFisheries.org flagship project is the Global Fisheries REST API forms the backbone of fisheries data science, enabling reproducible analytics in R (R Core Team, 2019), Python or any other language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting chlorophyll value in the Pemba channel with the prophet package in R</title>
      <link>/05/31/2019/forecasting-chlorophyll-value-in-the-pemba-channel-with-the-prophet-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/31/2019/forecasting-chlorophyll-value-in-the-pemba-channel-with-the-prophet-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>introductionTime series analysis comprises methods for predicting the future based on the historical in order to extract meaningful statistics and other characteristics of the data. In other words, time series forecasting is the use of a model to predict future values based on previously observed values. Time series are widely used for non-stationary data, like economic, weather, stock price, and retail sales in this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Access, Download, Process and VIsualize sea surface height and geostrophic current from AVISO in R</title>
      <link>/04/15/2019/access-download-process-and-visualize-sea-surface-height-and-geostrophic-current-from-aviso-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/04/15/2019/access-download-process-and-visualize-sea-surface-height-and-geostrophic-current-from-aviso-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In this post I explain how to read the NetCDF file of aviso in R. I also showed how to make plot of the processed sea surface height with ggplot2 package (Wickham 2016) and also animated a series of map with gganimate packages (Pedersen and Robinson 2017). However, the link that I used to obtain the data is no longer active and people find difficult to follow the instructions in the post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting streamlines of surface current with ggplot2 and metR package</title>
      <link>/03/20/2019/plotting-streamlines-of-surface-current-with-ggplot2-and-metr-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/20/2019/plotting-streamlines-of-surface-current-with-ggplot2-and-metr-package/</guid>
      <description>One major task for scientists in their daily routine is to prepare graphics for technical document, reports or manuscripts for publication. Graphics in form of figures carry the weight of the arguments. They need to be clear, attractive and convincing. according to [@], the difference between good and bad figures always lead into the difference between a highly influential or an obscure paper; a grant/contract won or lost; and a job interview gone well or poorly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dygraphs for interactive time series oceanographical data</title>
      <link>/03/18/2019/interactive-time-series-of-in-situ-sea-surface-temperature-with-dygraphs-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/18/2019/interactive-time-series-of-in-situ-sea-surface-temperature-with-dygraphs-package/</guid>
      <description>Interactive plots can help users overcome the dilemma of complex or detailed plot like the hour temperature records plotted over a year. They also offers readers an option or tools to explore the plot in detail. R has several package that turn static plot into interactive ones. In this post, I will show you how to create an interactive time series using the dygraphs package developed and maintained by Vanderkam et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Time Series Data in R</title>
      <link>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionShumway and Stoffer (2017) in the book with a title Time series analysis and its applications: with R examples clearly stated that when dealing with any time series analysis the first step you ought to do befure further investigation is careful examination of the recorded data. This means before looking more closely at the particular statistical methods, it is appropriate to plot the recorded data against time. This scrutiny often suggests the method of analysis as well as statistics that will be of use in summarizing the information in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>publishing code into Technical Report</title>
      <link>/02/22/2019/publishing-code-into-technical-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/22/2019/publishing-code-into-technical-report/</guid>
      <description>You are creating a report based on some analysis you are doing in R. You are pasting code snippes and figures into your report document. The document is reviewed and you got comments and feedback of something went wrong in your report and you ought to redo it all over again.
The publishing tools in Rstudio allows you to run a script and automaticaly generate document containing the results, including images of each figures generated and imported; the code chunk and code blocks with text and mathematical equations that you insert and inserting references cited.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Isosurface of temperature, salinity, oxygen and fluorescence in Mafia Channel from CTD data </title>
      <link>/02/12/2019/isosurface-of-temperature-salinity-oxygen-and-fluorescence-in-mafia-channel-from-ctd-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/12/2019/isosurface-of-temperature-salinity-oxygen-and-fluorescence-in-mafia-channel-from-ctd-data/</guid>
      <description>Iso surfaceOften times we want to visualize the distribution of oceanographic variables across the space at specific depth. That kind of visualization refers to isosurface—layer(s) of constant values of another data variable, such as, constant depth. For this post highlights key steps to create isosurface from CTD profile data in Mafia channel. Because these channel is shallow with an average depth of 20 meters, we will calculate isosurface of f temperature, oxygen, fluorescene at the surface, 10 and 20 meters deep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detect the Mixed Layer Depth (MLD)  along the East African Coastal Current  from   Argo floats data using criterion approach</title>
      <link>/02/01/2019/compute-the-mixed-layer-depth-mld-along-the-east-african-coastal-current-from-argo-floats-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/01/2019/compute-the-mixed-layer-depth-mld-along-the-east-african-coastal-current-from-argo-floats-data/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe ocean mixed layer is narrow band of the suface water that is homogenous—where temperature, salinity and density scarcely vary with increasing depth (Costoya et al. 2014). This homogeneity layer is caused by turbulent vertical mixing that is driven by heat loss from the ocean to the atmosphere and wind stress. The deepest layer affected by this turbulent mixing is called mixed layer depth (MLD), which marks the width of the upper ocean that interacts with the atmosphere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming: An Essential Skills for Scientists</title>
      <link>/11/23/2018/programming-an-essential-skills-for-scientists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/23/2018/programming-an-essential-skills-for-scientists/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn recent years, there’s been an admirable push to get more people to learn programming. But if I’ve never been exposed to programming, why should I invest all of the effort to learn? What’s in it for me? When I was confronted with data limitation challenge in spreadsheet (Brown, 2001), and the issue of repeating the same process over and over again, I decided to learn to program. I started learning R— a statistical and graphical software (James, Witten, Hastie, &amp;amp; Tibshirani, 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing Our Academic  Dissertation to Broad Audiences</title>
      <link>/11/14/2018/publishing-our-academic-dissertation-to-broad-audiences/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/14/2018/publishing-our-academic-dissertation-to-broad-audiences/</guid>
      <description>For years I used Word Processors to prepare manuscript for publication and report. And I used Adobe Indesign whenever I was consulted for typsetting and layout of the books. Adobe suite—a combination of design software was a tool that I often used in my machine. These tools includes Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Indesign and Adobe Illustrator. I prepared the text in Microsoft word and imported it into Indesign for typesetting and layout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read netCDF file with in R</title>
      <link>/11/07/2018/read-netcdf-file-with-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/07/2018/read-netcdf-file-with-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In the previously post, I covered how to read and convert netCDF files directly into R and convert to data frames. The approach is simple and straight forward but there flaws in this approach. One main setback of this approach is its inability to read maltiple matrix in an array from a netcdf file. This inability end up obtain a data frame from the of the first matrice of an array dropping out other matrix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read and Convert netcdf files into data frame in R</title>
      <link>/11/03/2018/converting-netcdf-files-into-data-frame/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/03/2018/converting-netcdf-files-into-data-frame/</guid>
      <description>Scientist often store most of oceanographic and environmental variables from satellite sensors in netCDF format. The netCDF data file format contain one or more variables, which are usually structured as regular arrays and metadata describing the contents and format of the data. For example, you might have a variable named “Temperature” that is a function of longitude, latitude, and depth. NetCDF files also contain dimensions, which describe the extent of the variables’ arrays.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animating Oceanographic data in R with ggplot2 and gganimate</title>
      <link>/10/29/2018/animating-oceanographic-data-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-gganimate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/29/2018/animating-oceanographic-data-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-gganimate/</guid>
      <description>setwd(&amp;quot;E:/Data Manipulation/xtractomatic&amp;quot;)IntroductionThe increasing popularity of ggplot2 package (Wickham, 2016) had made many people becomes familiar with art of grammer of graphics of static plots. But, most of environmental data are static but rather changes both with time and space. Therefore, animated plots are effective way to communicate these dind of data.
Pedersen &amp;amp; Robinson (2017) developed gganimate package that extends the grammar of graphic as implemented with ggplot2 with animations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing Satellite Wind Speed Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/25/2018/processing-satellite-wind-speed-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/25/2018/processing-satellite-wind-speed-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>The Advanced Scatterometer (ASCAT) winds products are processed by NOAA/NESDIS utilizing measurements from the scatterometer instrument aboard the EUMETSAT Metop satellites. The instrument uses radar to measure backscatter to determine speed and direction of winds over the surface of the oceans. ASCAT observations fields have regular spatial resolutions of 0.25° in longitude and latitude.
The daily wind fields are calculated in near real time with a delay of 48 hours.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface current in the Tropical Indian Ocean Region from Drifter Observations</title>
      <link>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the previous post I showed how to track the East African Coastal Current using trajectories od drifters. In this post, we dive deeper, focusing on creating grids and fill them with number of drifter the median surface current and present them in form of maps. The goal of this routine is to illustrate how to process drifter data in R using tidyverse and other packages.
Needed PackagesWe need to load some packages into R that are used to process the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The East African Coastal Current captured with satellite-tracked drifter observations</title>
      <link>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</guid>
      <description>My interest to explore the EACC comes from its role in linking the boundary currents north of Madagascar and at the equator. It is long established that the East African Coastal Current flows northward along the coast of Tanzania throughout the year1. However, until now we have a rough sketch of the East african coastal current and its seanoal variations. In this post, I am going to illustrate to you how to process drifter data that capture nicely the pathways of the EACC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface Current in Pemba channel: Drifter Perspective</title>
      <link>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionSurface Currents are driven by global wind systems that are fueled by energy from the sun1. These currents inturn transfer heat from the tropics to the polar regions, influencing local and global climate2. Ocean currents are an important abiotic factor that significantly influences food webs and reproduction of marine organisms and the marine ecosystems that they inhabit3. Many species with limited mobility depend on this “liquid wind” to bring food and nutrients to them and to distribute larvae and reproductive cells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing CTD measurements in R with Oce and tidyverse packages</title>
      <link>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I illustrate how to process ship-based CTD data with oce1 package in R2 enviroment. We saw the power of this package in reading, summarizing and visualizing CTD data. The downside of oce package in my opinion is its strickest nature of relying on R base for data processing and plotting—preventing customization. Therefore, in this post I will illustrate how to tranforming oce dataset format into a tibble—a modern data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating MODIS Sea Surface Temperature with Global Drifter Program Observations</title>
      <link>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post, I am going to illustrate routines of how to validate sea surface temperatures from Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) with drifters’ sea surface temperature. Drifters measurements serve as in-situ data against MODIS data. The purpose is to assess closeneness (accuracy) of satellite and in-situ SST. I will check the accuracy of acquired (satellite) and measured (drifter) SST, visualize their relationship and test the significance of the relationship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>