<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Algoa on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/algoa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Algoa on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/algoa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographical coordinates conversion made easy with parzer package in R</title>
      <link>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Geographic coordinates are often in “degrees” but they can also include “minutes” and “seconds”. This gives us a variety of different formats for reporting the coordinates and you’ll see that different groups will use different formats. Computers do not really work well with DMS coordinates and we really prefer the coordinates to be in Decimal Degrees or DD.
This format allows us to perform standard decimal math operations on the coordinates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing classical methods for estimating the mixed layer depth along the transect off Kimbiji, Tanzania</title>
      <link>/02/09/2019/comparing-classical-methods-for-estimating-the-mixed-layer-depth-along-the-transect-off-kimbiji-tanzania/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/09/2019/comparing-classical-methods-for-estimating-the-mixed-layer-depth-along-the-transect-off-kimbiji-tanzania/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionUpper Ocean is characterized for a quasi-homogeneous layer where temperature, salinity and density almost constant with increasing depth (Costoya et al. 2014). This homogeneity layer is caused by turbulent vertical mixing that is driven by heat loss from the ocean to the atmosphere, as well as by wind stress (Stranne et al. 2018). The deepest layer affected by this turbulent mixing is called mixed layer depth (MLD), which marks the width of the upper ocean that interacts with the atmosphere (Kelley 2018).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Mixed Layer Depth with Optimal Linear fitting method.</title>
      <link>/02/08/2019/different-approaches-of-detecting-mixed-layer-depth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/08/2019/different-approaches-of-detecting-mixed-layer-depth/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe mixed layer is a thin layer with constant temperature and salinity from the surface down to a depth where the values differ from those at the surface (Boyer Montégut et al. 2004). Wind blowing on the ocean stirs the upper layers leading to a thin mixed layer (Stewart 2008). The resulting surface mixed layer is important for local primary production, climate and ocean circulation (Kelley 2018). Although the mixed layer is an important oceanographic parameter, there different approaches that are used and each method depends on the scientific application.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>