<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pressure on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/pressure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pressure on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/pressure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Isosurface of temperature, salinity, oxygen and fluorescence in Mafia Channel from CTD data </title>
      <link>/02/12/2019/isosurface-of-temperature-salinity-oxygen-and-fluorescence-in-mafia-channel-from-ctd-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/12/2019/isosurface-of-temperature-salinity-oxygen-and-fluorescence-in-mafia-channel-from-ctd-data/</guid>
      <description>Iso surfaceOften times we want to visualize the distribution of oceanographic variables across the space at specific depth. That kind of visualization refers to isosurface—layer(s) of constant values of another data variable, such as, constant depth. For this post highlights key steps to create isosurface from CTD profile data in Mafia channel. Because these channel is shallow with an average depth of 20 meters, we will calculate isosurface of f temperature, oxygen, fluorescene at the surface, 10 and 20 meters deep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CTD Data in R with oce and tidyverse package</title>
      <link>/10/05/2018/ctd-data-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/05/2018/ctd-data-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-package/</guid>
      <description>Introductionin the previous post, we looked at CTD processing and visualization of profile and section with oce package. We saw the necessary tools needed to import, transform and even plotting oceanographic standard graphics. This post introduce to an ecosystem of packages called tidyverse. The three packages in tidyverse that people use in everyday data analyses include the grammer for graphic ggplot develop by Wickham (2016) for data visualization.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>