<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Semba on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/semba/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Semba on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/semba/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Access meteorogical observations using worldmet package</title>
      <link>/11/29/2019/access-meteorogical-observations-using-worldmet-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/29/2019/access-meteorogical-observations-using-worldmet-package/</guid>
      <description>David Carslaw (2019) developed R package worldmet, which provides an easy way to access world meteorological data from from the Integrated Surface Database of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA). The Integrated Surface Database (ISD) consists of global hourly and synoptic observations compiled from numerous sources into a single common ASCII format and common data model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wordclouds plotting with ggwordcloud package in R</title>
      <link>/11/05/2019/wordclouds-plotting-with-ggwordcloud-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/05/2019/wordclouds-plotting-with-ggwordcloud-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, we saw how to make wordcloud graphic using the wordcloud package. In this post we extend the ability of R to make wordcloud graphic, but rather than using the base R function for plotting,I will show how to use ggplot2 framework.
Le Pennec and Slowikowski (2019) developed a gwordcloud package, which extend the capability of ggplot2 package (Wickham 2016) of making cloud text. With the geom_text_wordcloud() function, gwordcloud made making wordcloud plot easy with ggplot2 package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A glimpse of FAO&#39; fisheries statistics in R</title>
      <link>/10/16/2019/a-glimpse-of-fao-fisheries-statistics-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/16/2019/a-glimpse-of-fao-fisheries-statistics-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe OpenFisheries.org project created an open web platform aimed to advance the practice of data science in fisheries. The project has managed to consolidate global fisheries dataset that can be accessed and retrieved using modern analytics. The OpenFisheries.org flagship project is the Global Fisheries REST API forms the backbone of fisheries data science, enabling reproducible analytics in R (R Core Team, 2019), Python or any other language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting time series data with R</title>
      <link>/08/09/2019/forecasting-time-series-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/08/09/2019/forecasting-time-series-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>introductionIn this post I illustrate how to predict the future using the historical data. Time series analysis comprises methods for predicting the future based on the historical in order to extract meaningful statistics and other characteristics of the data. In other words, time series forecasting is the use of a model to predict future values based on previously observed values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pie chart and Donut plot with ggplot2</title>
      <link>/07/12/2019/pie-chart-and-donut-plot-with-ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/07/12/2019/pie-chart-and-donut-plot-with-ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>Introductionggplot2 packaged for R developed by Hadley Wickham (2016) provides powerful functions for plotting high quality graphs in R.This package has many functions for creating plots among them are pies and donut charts. Pie charts are widely used for showing proportions of mutually–exclusive categories. A pie chart is a circular graphic divided into slices to illustrate numerical proportion of the categorial variable. In a pie chart, the length of each slice is equivalent to the counts or proportion of that slice.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>