<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Information Technology on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/information-technology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Information Technology on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/information-technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Model and Project the death toll of coronavirus at Wuhan Province in R</title>
      <link>/02/08/2020/model-and-project-the-death-toll-of-coronavirus-at-wuhan-province-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/08/2020/model-and-project-the-death-toll-of-coronavirus-at-wuhan-province-in-r/</guid>
      <description>require(tidyverse)require(modelr)require(magrittr)require(gam)require(sf)IntroductionThis tutorial will show you how to scrape that data from html table, which lives in a wikipedia and download the data for further processing. Let us load the packages we need for the session
Figure 1: The map showing the spread of coronavirusDataThe data for this analysis was obtained from the Wikipedia page that provide updates of people died with coronavirus in Wuhan province.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plotting the Spatial distribution of Chlorophyll in Mafia Channel from MODIS</title>
      <link>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</guid>
      <description>Making graphics and maps is one of the important skills for oceanographers and marine scientists. Maps are often used by scientists to locate areas of interest—where the study being presented was conducted. Thus ability to make maps that convey the message in a simple manner form an important first impression for readers. Despite this, software tools for producing high-quality maps are non-trivial to use.
In this post I illustrate how some key lines of code for access, download and map the spatial distribution of chlorophyll-a concentration within the Rufiji-Mafia Channel using a combination of packages in the R environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things I learned in TAFIRI R Workshop 2019</title>
      <link>/06/17/2019/things-i-learned-in-tafiri-r-workshop-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/06/17/2019/things-i-learned-in-tafiri-r-workshop-2019/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionWe had a three days workshop on using R for analytical framework from 12th to 14th July, 2019 at the headquarter of Tanzania Fisheries Reseach Institute (TAFIRI), Dar es Salaam. The workshop was a follow up of similar training conducted in July, 2018. Though the focus of the workshop relied on the base R syntax that does not allow you to express succinctly the coding with pipping, I can honestly say it was one of the most interesting and educational training.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Access, Download, Process and VIsualize sea surface height and geostrophic current from AVISO in R</title>
      <link>/04/15/2019/access-download-process-and-visualize-sea-surface-height-and-geostrophic-current-from-aviso-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/04/15/2019/access-download-process-and-visualize-sea-surface-height-and-geostrophic-current-from-aviso-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In this post I explain how to read the NetCDF file of aviso in R. I also showed how to make plot of the processed sea surface height with ggplot2 package (Wickham 2016) and also animated a series of map with gganimate packages (Pedersen and Robinson 2017). However, the link that I used to obtain the data is no longer active and people find difficult to follow the instructions in the post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting streamlines of surface current with ggplot2 and metR package</title>
      <link>/03/20/2019/plotting-streamlines-of-surface-current-with-ggplot2-and-metr-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/20/2019/plotting-streamlines-of-surface-current-with-ggplot2-and-metr-package/</guid>
      <description>One major task for scientists in their daily routine is to prepare graphics for technical document, reports or manuscripts for publication. Graphics in form of figures carry the weight of the arguments. They need to be clear, attractive and convincing. according to [@], the difference between good and bad figures always lead into the difference between a highly influential or an obscure paper; a grant/contract won or lost; and a job interview gone well or poorly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dygraphs for interactive time series oceanographical data</title>
      <link>/03/18/2019/interactive-time-series-of-in-situ-sea-surface-temperature-with-dygraphs-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/18/2019/interactive-time-series-of-in-situ-sea-surface-temperature-with-dygraphs-package/</guid>
      <description>Interactive plots can help users overcome the dilemma of complex or detailed plot like the hour temperature records plotted over a year. They also offers readers an option or tools to explore the plot in detail. R has several package that turn static plot into interactive ones. In this post, I will show you how to create an interactive time series using the dygraphs package developed and maintained by Vanderkam et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Reasons for Creating my blog!</title>
      <link>/02/19/2019/why-i-created-a-static-blog-from-scratch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/19/2019/why-i-created-a-static-blog-from-scratch/</guid>
      <description>According to firstpage;
…blogging was initially used as a unique platform to share a person’s thoughts, feelings, opinions or experiences—an online journal or diary with a minimal following.
Today, it has grown into a platform used by millions, everyone from individuals to businesses. The simplicity of a blog makes it easy for anyone to launch a blog and become a self-proclaimed “expert.” But how is it important in the world today, with unprecedented advent in technology and computing?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>