<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistics on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistics on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A glimpse of FAO&#39; fisheries statistics in R</title>
      <link>/10/16/2019/a-glimpse-of-fao-fisheries-statistics-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/16/2019/a-glimpse-of-fao-fisheries-statistics-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe OpenFisheries.org project created an open web platform aimed to advance the practice of data science in fisheries. The project has managed to consolidate global fisheries dataset that can be accessed and retrieved using modern analytics. The OpenFisheries.org flagship project is the Global Fisheries REST API forms the backbone of fisheries data science, enabling reproducible analytics in R (R Core Team, 2019), Python or any other language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dygraphs for interactive time series oceanographical data</title>
      <link>/03/18/2019/interactive-time-series-of-in-situ-sea-surface-temperature-with-dygraphs-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/18/2019/interactive-time-series-of-in-situ-sea-surface-temperature-with-dygraphs-package/</guid>
      <description>Interactive plots can help users overcome the dilemma of complex or detailed plot like the hour temperature records plotted over a year. They also offers readers an option or tools to explore the plot in detail. R has several package that turn static plot into interactive ones. In this post, I will show you how to create an interactive time series using the dygraphs package developed and maintained by Vanderkam et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Time Series Data in R</title>
      <link>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionShumway and Stoffer (2017) in the book with a title Time series analysis and its applications: with R examples clearly stated that when dealing with any time series analysis the first step you ought to do befure further investigation is careful examination of the recorded data. This means before looking more closely at the particular statistical methods, it is appropriate to plot the recorded data against time. This scrutiny often suggests the method of analysis as well as statistics that will be of use in summarizing the information in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time series analysis in R</title>
      <link>/02/20/2019/time-series-analysis-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/20/2019/time-series-analysis-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Any quantitative value measured over regular time intervals makes a Time Series. Time-series analysis aims to investigate the temporal behavior of a variable \(X_{t}\). Examples include the investigation of long-term records of sea surface temperature, sea-level fluctuations, millennium-scale variations in the atmosphere-ocean system, the eff ect of the El-Niño/Southern Oscillation on tropical rainfall and sedimentation (Trauth 2015). R has extensive facilities for analyzing time series data. These packages provides various tools with which to detect these temporal patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>