<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrate R and Python in Rstudio to Power Your Analytical Capability</title>
      <link>/07/10/2020/integrate-r-and-python-in-rstudio-to-power-your-analytical-capability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/07/10/2020/integrate-r-and-python-in-rstudio-to-power-your-analytical-capability/</guid>
      <description>If you work with data science, R and Python must be the two programming languages that you use the most. Both R and Python are quite robust languages and either one of them is actually sufficient to carry out the data analysis task. However, instead of considering them as tools that supplement each other, more often you will find people dealing with data claim one language to be better than the other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping with cartopy in python</title>
      <link>/07/04/2020/mapping-with-cartopy-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/07/04/2020/mapping-with-cartopy-in-python/</guid>
      <description>Today we will learn about Cartopy, one of the most common packages for making maps within python. Another popular and powerful library is Basemap; however, Basemap is going away and being replaced with Cartopy in the near future, For this reason, investing your time in learning mapping in python with Cartopy module is recommended.
We thank Research in Computing Earth Sciences because most of material in this post are gleaned from their website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python as a tool for oceagraphy and marine sciences</title>
      <link>/07/02/2020/python-as-a-tool-for-oceagraphy-and-marine-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/07/02/2020/python-as-a-tool-for-oceagraphy-and-marine-sciences/</guid>
      <description>During the last couple of decades, Matlab has been the most commonly-used scripting language in physical oceanography (Bengtsson 2018), and it has a large user base in many other fields. However, Python has been gaining ground, often being adopted by former Matlab users as well as by newcomers. Here is a little background to help you understand this shift, and why we advocate using Python from the start.
Python was designed by a computer scientist as a general–purpose scripting language for easy adoption and widespread use.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>