<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mafia Channel on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/mafia-channel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mafia Channel on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/mafia-channel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Detect the Mixed Layer Depth (MLD)  along the East African Coastal Current  from   Argo floats data using criterion approach</title>
      <link>/02/01/2019/compute-the-mixed-layer-depth-mld-along-the-east-african-coastal-current-from-argo-floats-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/01/2019/compute-the-mixed-layer-depth-mld-along-the-east-african-coastal-current-from-argo-floats-data/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe ocean mixed layer is narrow band of the suface water that is homogenous—where temperature, salinity and density scarcely vary with increasing depth (Costoya et al. 2014). This homogeneity layer is caused by turbulent vertical mixing that is driven by heat loss from the ocean to the atmosphere and wind stress. The deepest layer affected by this turbulent mixing is called mixed layer depth (MLD), which marks the width of the upper ocean that interacts with the atmosphere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing ADCP Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe Second International Indian Ocean Expedition (IIOE-2) collected various oceanographic data within the coastal water of Tanzania. Among the oceanographic data collected using Agulhas II, is the Acoustic Doppler Current Profiles (ADCP). The measurement was carried out from 4th to 9th November 2017. In this post, I will illustrate how to process the ADCP data with R using oce package developed by Kelley &amp;amp; Richards (2018).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing  CTD data with OCE package in R</title>
      <link>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Oceanographers love MATLAB\(^\circledR\) for processing oceanographic data. I have no explanation as to why they love Matlab. I suppose it’s been the de facto standard within the field for a long time, and legacy is a big deal. I have used Matlab for data processing and plotting for several years. With MatLab I implemented a vast amount of tools and rather completed numerical models. Being a self sponsored graduate student at an institution that doesn’t have a subscription, I found sticking to Matlab not only is expensive, but also unsustainable.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>