<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Satellite on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/satellite/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Satellite on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/satellite/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Wind in the western Indian ocean region</title>
      <link>/10/23/2018/wind-in-the-western-indian-ocean-region/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/23/2018/wind-in-the-western-indian-ocean-region/</guid>
      <description>The list of erddap data set and server are found at https://coastwatch.pfeg.noaa.gov/erddap/metadata/fgdc/xml/.
Comparisons of Wind StressA problem faced when using satellite based estimates of wind stress is that the QuikSCAT based estimates start in 1999-07-21 and end in 2009-11-19, while the ASCAT based estimates start in 2009-10-03 and are ongoing. A comparison of the data over the period of overlap would be of interest.
require(sf)require(tidyverse)require(lubridate)require(oce)require(rerddap)require(gganimate)extract centroid from polygones</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal Climatology of temperature and salinity in the WIO region from Argo floats </title>
      <link>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionFor years oceanographers have measured temperature and salinity from the surface to the ocean bottom (Foster, 1983). However, our ability to obtain reliable temperature and salinity profiles at fairly resolution both in location and time has been improved through the use of profiling floats from the Argo program (Roemmich et al., 2009; Rosell-Fieschi, 2014; Vilibić &amp;amp; Mihanović, 2013). The Argo program started in the early 2000s with the prime objective of monitoring the upper layer of the world oceans (Rosell-Fieschi, 2014).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drifter-derived seasonal climatology of Sea surface temperature in the Tropical Indian Ocean</title>
      <link>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</guid>
      <description>The study of sea surface temperature (SST) is one of the cornerstone of oceanography. It has applications not only in physics (Bader &amp;amp; Latif, 2003), chemistry (Corrège, 2006) and the earth’s sciences, but in subjects as diverse as biology and economics. SST plays an important role in our quantitative understanding of coastal habitats and species distribution in our global oceans (Grémillet et al., 2008; Müller-Karger, Walsh, Evans, &amp;amp; Meyers, 1991).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface current in the Tropical Indian Ocean Region from Drifter Observations</title>
      <link>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the previous post I showed how to track the East African Coastal Current using trajectories od drifters. In this post, we dive deeper, focusing on creating grids and fill them with number of drifter the median surface current and present them in form of maps. The goal of this routine is to illustrate how to process drifter data in R using tidyverse and other packages.
Needed PackagesWe need to load some packages into R that are used to process the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The East African Coastal Current captured with satellite-tracked drifter observations</title>
      <link>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</guid>
      <description>My interest to explore the EACC comes from its role in linking the boundary currents north of Madagascar and at the equator. It is long established that the East African Coastal Current flows northward along the coast of Tanzania throughout the year1. However, until now we have a rough sketch of the East african coastal current and its seanoal variations. In this post, I am going to illustrate to you how to process drifter data that capture nicely the pathways of the EACC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating MODIS Sea Surface Temperature with Global Drifter Program Observations</title>
      <link>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post, I am going to illustrate routines of how to validate sea surface temperatures from Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) with drifters’ sea surface temperature. Drifters measurements serve as in-situ data against MODIS data. The purpose is to assess closeneness (accuracy) of satellite and in-situ SST. I will check the accuracy of acquired (satellite) and measured (drifter) SST, visualize their relationship and test the significance of the relationship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>