<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mapping on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/mapping/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mapping on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/mapping/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping with cartopy in python</title>
      <link>/07/04/2020/mapping-with-cartopy-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/07/04/2020/mapping-with-cartopy-in-python/</guid>
      <description>Today we will learn about Cartopy, one of the most common packages for making maps within python. Another popular and powerful library is Basemap; however, Basemap is going away and being replaced with Cartopy in the near future, For this reason, investing your time in learning mapping in python with Cartopy module is recommended.
We thank Research in Computing Earth Sciences because most of material in this post are gleaned from their website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Plots and  Maps in R</title>
      <link>/06/13/2020/plots-in-interactive-maps-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/06/13/2020/plots-in-interactive-maps-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionOften times when w are working with data, there always a geospatial component to the data—the locations. Most of us have used static maps to reveal information that other plots can not. And interactive maps can enliven geographic information to new insights. The most important type of interactivity, is the display of geographic data on interactive or ‘slippy’ web maps. Interactivity can take many forms, the most common and useful of which is the ability to pan around and zoom into any part of a geographic dataset overlaid on a ‘web map’ to show context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World map and Map projections</title>
      <link>/01/26/2020/world-map-and-map-projections/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/01/26/2020/world-map-and-map-projections/</guid>
      <description>A map projection is a way to flatten a globe’s surface into a plane in order to make a map. This requires a systematic transformation of the latitudes and longitudes of locations from the surface of the globe into locations on a plane.[1] All projections of a sphere on a plane necessarily distort the surface in some way and to some extent. Depending on the purpose of the map, some distortions are acceptable and others are not; therefore, different map projections exist in order to preserve some properties of the sphere-like body at the expense of other properties.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping with oce</title>
      <link>/02/13/2019/mapping-with-oce/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/13/2019/mapping-with-oce/</guid>
      <description>There are many different things that requires oceanographers to code and write scripts that automate routinely analytical frameworks. However, there is one common use amongst almost all every report, research project or paper will need to have—map indicating to a study area. There are many packages that are often used to make maps in R. And heaps of blog posts, books and tutorials that illustrate different ways to visualize spatial data in R.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>