<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Masumbuko Semba</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Masumbuko Semba</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>This blog is owned and operated by Masumbuko Semba. He is a data scientist works at the Nelson Mandela African Institution of Science and Technology but now doing a doctoral degree in physical oceanogrphy at the University of Dar es Salaam. He specializes in Earth Observations, where he use open-source geo-spatial tools and satellite observations to understand the physical processes that cause changes in our environments. Among the project he is involved is Global Drifter Program, where he works with the Physical Oceanographic Division of the Atlantic Oceanographic and Meteorological Laboratory (AOML) of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) to understnd the ocean circulation in the Tropical Indian Ocean region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Course I Offer</title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description>This blog is owned and operated by Masumbuko Semba. He is a data scientist works at the Nelson Mandela African Institution of Science and Technology but now doing a doctoral degree in physical oceanogrphy at the University of Dar es Salaam. He specializes in Earth Observations, where he use open-source geo-spatial tools and satellite observations to understand the physical processes that cause changes in our environments. Among the project he is involved is Global Drifter Program, where he works with the Physical Oceanographic Division of the Atlantic Oceanographic and Meteorological Laboratory (AOML) of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) to understnd the ocean circulation in the Tropical Indian Ocean region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/links/</guid>
      <description> R-bloggers  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>List of Publications</title>
      <link>/publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/</guid>
      <description>Semba M., Lumpkin R., Kimirei IA., Shaghude Y., &amp;amp; Nyandwi N (In press). Global Drifters’ Observations Reveal Seasonal Variations of Surface Current in the Pemba Channel. Plos One
 Mahatane, A., Yunus D. Mgaya, R. B. Hoza, P. O. Onyango, and Semba M (2017). &amp;ldquo;Co-management of Lake Victoria Fisheries.&amp;rdquo; In Lake Victoria Fisheries Resources : Research and Management in Tanzania, edited by Yunus D. Mgaya and Shigalla B. Mahongo, 219-39.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project</title>
      <link>/project---copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project---copy/</guid>
      <description>Sustainable Oceans, Livelihoods and food Security Through Increased Capacity in Ecosystem research in the Western Indian Ocean*   SOLSTICE-WIO is a four-year collaborative project funded by the UK Global Challenges Research Fund (GCRF). Launched in October 2017, it brings together local knowledge and international research expertise to address challenges facing the Western Indian Ocean (WIO) region in a cost-effective way.
  Estuarize-­WIO   A socio­‐ecological assessment of fisheries in three estuarine systems of the SW Indian Ocean – identifying essential links for improved governance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating MODIS Sea Surface Temperature with Global Drifter Program Observations</title>
      <link>/2018/09/20/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/20/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this routine, I am going to illustrate the routines of validating sea surface temperatures from Moderate resolution (MODIS) and drifters. Drifters serve as in-situ data against which the SST from MODIS is tested. The purpose is to assess how accurate the satellite observation is to the in-situ measurements. We will test the accuracy of the two dataset and look on their relationship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/2018/09/18/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/18/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/</guid>
      <description>Sustainable Oceans, Livelihoods and food Security Through Increased Capacity in Ecosystem research in the Western Indian Ocean*SOLSTICE-WIO is a four-year collaborative project funded by the UK Global Challenges Research Fund (GCRF). Launched in October 2017, it brings together local knowledge and international research expertise to address challenges facing the Western Indian Ocean region in a cost-effective way. SOLSTICE demonstrate its approach to strengthening research capacity through three case studies in Kenya, Tanzania and South Africa show in Figure 1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>