<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Masumbuko Semba</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Masumbuko Semba</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Masumbuko Semba is data scientist works at the Nelson Mandela African Institution of Science and Technology and doctoral student in physical oceanography at the University of Dar es Salaam. He specializes in Earth Observations and use open-source geo-spatial tools and satellite observations to address physical processes that brings changes in our environments. Among the project Semba is involved is Global Drifter Program. In this Project, he works with the Physical Oceanographic Division of the Atlantic Oceanographic and Meteorological Laboratory (AOML) of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) to understand the surface circulation dynamics in the Tropical Indian Ocean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Course I Offer</title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description>This blog is owned and operated by Masumbuko Semba. He is a data scientist works at the Nelson Mandela African Institution of Science and Technology but now doing a doctoral degree in physical oceanogrphy at the University of Dar es Salaam. He specializes in Earth Observations, where he use open-source geo-spatial tools and satellite observations to understand the physical processes that cause changes in our environments. Among the project he is involved is Global Drifter Program, where he works with the Physical Oceanographic Division of the Atlantic Oceanographic and Meteorological Laboratory (AOML) of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) to understnd the ocean circulation in the Tropical Indian Ocean region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/links/</guid>
      <description> R-bloggers  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>List of Publications</title>
      <link>/publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/</guid>
      <description>Semba M., Lumpkin R., Kimirei IA., Shaghude Y., &amp;amp; Nyandwi N (In press). Global Drifters’ Observations Reveal Seasonal Variations of Surface Current in the Pemba Channel. Plos One
 Mahatane, A., Yunus D. Mgaya, R. B. Hoza, P. O. Onyango, and Semba M (2017). &amp;ldquo;Co-management of Lake Victoria Fisheries.&amp;rdquo; In Lake Victoria Fisheries Resources : Research and Management in Tanzania, edited by Yunus D. Mgaya and Shigalla B. Mahongo, 219-39.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project</title>
      <link>/project---copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project---copy/</guid>
      <description>Sustainable Oceans, Livelihoods and food Security Through Increased Capacity in Ecosystem research in the Western Indian Ocean*   SOLSTICE-WIO is a four-year collaborative project funded by the UK Global Challenges Research Fund (GCRF). Launched in October 2017, it brings together local knowledge and international research expertise to address challenges facing the Western Indian Ocean (WIO) region in a cost-effective way.
  Estuarize-­WIO   A socio­‐ecological assessment of fisheries in three estuarine systems of the SW Indian Ocean – identifying essential links for improved governance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing ADCP Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe Second International Indian Ocean Expedition (IIOE-2) collected variaous oceanographic data within the coastal water of Tanzania. Among the oceanographic data collected using Agulhas II, is the Acoustic Doppler Current Profiles (ADCP). The measurement was carried out from 4th to 9th November 2017.
require(oce)require(ocedata)require(tidyverse)require(lubridate)require(leaflet)require(sf)adp = read.adp(&amp;quot;C:/Users/Semba/Documents/IIOE2/adcp/IIEO2/AGU028002_000000.LTA&amp;quot;)# summary(adp)time = adp[[&amp;quot;time&amp;quot;]]An ADCP (RD Instruments WH-Sentinel 300 kHz) was deployed ~25 km off the coast of Hokkaido (142°39.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CTD Data in R with oce and tidyverse package</title>
      <link>/10/05/2018/ctd-data-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/05/2018/ctd-data-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-package/</guid>
      <description>Introductionin the previous post, we looked at CTD processing and visualization of profile and section with oce package. We saw the necessary tools needed to import, transform and even plotting oceanographic standard graphics. This post introduce to an ecosystem of packages called tidyverse. The three packages in tidyverse that people use in everyday data analyses include the grammer for graphic ggplot develop by Wickham (2016) for data visualization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing  CTD data with OCE package in R</title>
      <link>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Oceanographers love MATLAB\(^\circledR\) for processing oceanographic data. I have no explanation as to why they love Matlab. I suppose it’s been the de facto standard within the field for a long time, and legacy is a big deal. I have used Matlab for data processing and plotting for several years. With MatLab I implemented a vast amount of tools and rather completed numerical models. Being a self sponsored graduate student at an institution that doesn’t have a subscription, I found sticking to Matlab not only is expensive, but also unsustainable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal Climatology of temperature and salinity in the WIO region from Argo floats </title>
      <link>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionFor years oceanographers have measured temperature and salinity from the surface to the ocean bottom (Foster, 1983). However, our ability to obtain reliable temperature and salinity profiles at fairly resolution both in location and time has been improved through the use of profiling floats from the Argo program (Roemmich et al., 2009; Rosell-Fieschi, 2014; Vilibić &amp;amp; Mihanović, 2013). The Argo program started in the early 2000s with the prime objective of monitoring the upper layer of the world oceans (Rosell-Fieschi, 2014).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear Model with R</title>
      <link>/10/02/2018/modelling-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/02/2018/modelling-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post I’am going to illustrate how to model in R. As Wickham &amp;amp; Grolemund1 put it
The prime goal of modeling is to provide simple low-dimension summary of a dataset.
I am not going to bring a novel science in this post but rather to help you learn the most important tools in R2 that will allow you to model your data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drifter-derived seasonal climatology of Sea surface temperature in the Tropical Indian Ocean</title>
      <link>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</guid>
      <description>The study of sea surface temperature (SST) is one of the cornerstone of oceanography. It has applications not only in physics (Bader &amp;amp; Latif, 2003), chemistry (Corrège, 2006) and the earth’s sciences, but in subjects as diverse as biology and economics. SST plays an important role in our quantitative understanding of coastal habitats and species distribution in our global oceans (Grémillet et al., 2008; Müller-Karger, Walsh, Evans, &amp;amp; Meyers, 1991).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface current in the Tropical Indian Ocean Region from Drifter Observations</title>
      <link>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the previous post I showed how to track the East African Coastal Current using trajectories od drifters. In this post, we dive deeper, focusing on creating grids and fill them with number of drifter the median surface current and present them in form of maps. The goal of this routine is to illustrate how to process drifter data in R using tidyverse and other packages.
Needed PackagesWe need to load some packages into R that are used to process the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The East African Coastal Current captured with satellite-tracked drifter observations</title>
      <link>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</guid>
      <description>My interest to explore the EACC comes from its role in linking the boundary currents north of Madagascar and at the equator. It is long established that the East African Coastal Current flows northward along the coast of Tanzania throughout the year1. However, until now we have a rough sketch of the East african coastal current and its seanoal variations. In this post, I am going to illustrate to you how to process drifter data that capture nicely the pathways of the EACC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface Current in Pemba channel: Drifter Perspective</title>
      <link>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionSurface Currents are driven by global wind systems that are fueled by energy from the sun1. These currents inturn transfer heat from the tropics to the polar regions, influencing local and global climate2. Ocean currents are an important abiotic factor that significantly influences food webs and reproduction of marine organisms and the marine ecosystems that they inhabit3. Many species with limited mobility depend on this “liquid wind” to bring food and nutrients to them and to distribute larvae and reproductive cells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing CTD measurements in R with Oce and tidyverse packages</title>
      <link>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I illustrate how to process ship-based CTD data with oce1 package in R2 enviroment. We saw the power of this package in reading, summarizing and visualizing CTD data. The downside of oce package in my opinion is its strickest nature of relying on R base for data processing and plotting—preventing customization. Therefore, in this post I will illustrate how to tranforming oce dataset format into a tibble—a modern data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing ship-based CTD measurements in Pemba Channel with R</title>
      <link>/09/21/2018/vertical-structure-of-temperature-salinity-and-fluorescence-of-the-pemba-channel-from-ctd-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/21/2018/vertical-structure-of-temperature-salinity-and-fluorescence-of-the-pemba-channel-from-ctd-measurements/</guid>
      <description>This post introduces to simple analysis of CTD data using oce1 package in R2 environment. CTD stands for conductivity, temperature, and depth, and refers to a package of electronic instruments that measure these properties.A CTD device’s primary function is to detect how the conductivity and temperature of the water column changes relative to depth. Conductivity is a measure of how well a solution conducts electricity. Conductivity is directly related to salinity, which is the concentration of salt and other inorganic compounds in seawater.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating MODIS Sea Surface Temperature with Global Drifter Program Observations</title>
      <link>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post, I am going to illustrate routines of how to validate sea surface temperatures from Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) with drifters’ sea surface temperature. Drifters measurements serve as in-situ data against MODIS data. The purpose is to assess closeneness (accuracy) of satellite and in-situ SST. I will check the accuracy of acquired (satellite) and measured (drifter) SST, visualize their relationship and test the significance of the relationship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/</guid>
      <description>Sustainable Oceans, Livelihoods and food Security Through Increased Capacity in Ecosystem research in the Western Indian Ocean*SOLSTICE-WIO is a four-year collaborative project funded by the UK Global Challenges Research Fund (GCRF). Launched in October 2017, it brings together local knowledge and international research expertise to address challenges facing the Western Indian Ocean region in a cost-effective way. SOLSTICE demonstrate its approach to strengthening research capacity through three case studies in Kenya, Tanzania and South Africa show in Figure 1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>