<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Masumbuko Semba works at the Nelson Mandela African Institution of Science and Technology as data scientist and a doctoral student in physical oceanography at the University of Dar es Salaam.
Semba specializes in coding using various programming languages. Coding is nothing more than telling a computer what to do in a language the computer understands. Semba created this blog to offer some ground-breaking solutions using open source programming languages affordable worldwide even to third world’s countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/links/</guid>
      <description> R-bloggers  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>List of Publications</title>
      <link>/publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/</guid>
      <description>Semba M., Lumpkin R., Kimirei I., Shaghude Y., &amp;amp; Nyandwi N (2019). Seasonal and Spatial variation of Surface Current in the Pemba Channel, Tanzania. PLOS ONE 14 (1):e0210303. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0210303.
Peter, N., Semba, M., Lugomela, C., &amp;amp; Kyewalyanga, M. S. (2018). The influence of physical-chemical variables on the spatial and seasonal variation of Chlorophyll-a in coastal waters of Unguja, Zanzibar, Tanzania. Western Indian Ocean Journal of Marine Science, 17(2), 25-34.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masumbuko Semba</title>
      <link>/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/resume/</guid>
      <description>Employment Position: Assistant Lecturer
Insitute: Nelson Mandela African Institution of Science and Technology, P. O. Box 447, Arusha, Tanzania
Education 2016-2019: PhD in Physical Oceanography - University of Dar es Salaam
2009-2011: Master of Marine Sciences - University of Dar es Salaam
2004-2007: Bachelor Degree in Fisheries and Aquaculture - University of Dar es Salaam
Extracurricular Activities Writer: Write online and digital books on data analyis and programming.
Designing graphic: Design graphics and typeset books</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project</title>
      <link>/project-copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project-copy/</guid>
      <description>Sustainable Oceans, Livelihoods and food Security Through Increased Capacity in Ecosystem research in the Western Indian Ocean*   SOLSTICE-WIO is a four-year collaborative project funded by the UK Global Challenges Research Fund (GCRF). Launched in October 2017, it brings together local knowledge and international research expertise to address challenges facing the Western Indian Ocean (WIO) region in a cost-effective way.
  Estuarize-­WIO   A socio­‐ecological assessment of fisheries in three estuarine systems of the SW Indian Ocean – identifying essential links for improved governance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming: An Essential Skills for Scientists</title>
      <link>/11/23/2018/programming-an-essential-skills-for-scientists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/23/2018/programming-an-essential-skills-for-scientists/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn recent years, there’s been an admirable push to get more people to learn programming. But if I’ve never been exposed to programming, why should I invest all of the effort to learn? What’s in it for me? When I was confronted with data limitation challenge in spreadsheet (Brown, 2001), and the issue of repeating the same process over and over again, I decided to learn to program. I started learning R— a statistical and graphical software (James, Witten, Hastie, &amp;amp; Tibshirani, 2013).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publishing Our Academic  Dissertation to Broad Audiences</title>
      <link>/11/14/2018/publishing-our-academic-dissertation-to-broad-audiences/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/14/2018/publishing-our-academic-dissertation-to-broad-audiences/</guid>
      <description>For years I used Word Processors to prepare manuscript for publication and report. And I used Adobe Indesign whenever I was consulted for typsetting and layout of the books. Adobe suite—a combination of design software was a tool that I often used in my machine. These tools includes Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Indesign and Adobe Illustrator. I prepared the text in Microsoft word and imported it into Indesign for typesetting and layout.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read netCDF file with in R</title>
      <link>/11/07/2018/read-netcdf-file-with-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/07/2018/read-netcdf-file-with-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In the previously post, I covered how to read and convert netCDF files directly into R and convert to data frames. The approach is simple and straight forward but there flaws in this approach. One main setback of this approach is its inability to read maltiple matrix in an array from a netcdf file. This inability end up obtain a data frame from the of the first matrice of an array dropping out other matrix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read and Convert netcdf files into data frame in R</title>
      <link>/11/03/2018/converting-netcdf-files-into-data-frame/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/11/03/2018/converting-netcdf-files-into-data-frame/</guid>
      <description>Scientist often store most of oceanographic and environmental variables from satellite sensors in netCDF format. The netCDF data file format contain one or more variables, which are usually structured as regular arrays and metadata describing the contents and format of the data. For example, you might have a variable named “Temperature” that is a function of longitude, latitude, and depth. NetCDF files also contain dimensions, which describe the extent of the variables’ arrays.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animating Oceanographic data in R with ggplot2 and gganimate</title>
      <link>/10/29/2018/animating-oceanographic-data-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-gganimate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/29/2018/animating-oceanographic-data-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-gganimate/</guid>
      <description>setwd(&amp;quot;E:/Data Manipulation/xtractomatic&amp;quot;)IntroductionThe increasing popularity of ggplot2 package (Wickham, 2016) had made many people becomes familiar with art of grammer of graphics of static plots. But, most of environmental data are static but rather changes both with time and space. Therefore, animated plots are effective way to communicate these dind of data.
Pedersen &amp;amp; Robinson (2017) developed gganimate package that extends the grammar of graphic as implemented with ggplot2 with animations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Access and Process Quikscat Wind speed and direction with R</title>
      <link>/10/27/2018/access-and-process-quikscat-wind-speed-and-direction-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/27/2018/access-and-process-quikscat-wind-speed-and-direction-with-r/</guid>
      <description>quikscatIn his An Introduction to the Near–Real–Time QuikSCAT Data, Hoffman (2005) described the primary mission of the SeaWinds instrument on the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Quick Scatterometer (QuikSCAT ) satellite was to retrieve the surface vector wind over the global ocean (Lungu 2001).
QuikSCAT has provided an extremely accurate and extraordinarily comprehensive view of the surface wind over the global ocean since July 1999 (Chelton et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing Satellite Wind Speed Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/25/2018/processing-satellite-wind-speed-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/25/2018/processing-satellite-wind-speed-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>The Advanced Scatterometer (ASCAT) winds products are processed by NOAA/NESDIS utilizing measurements from the scatterometer instrument aboard the EUMETSAT Metop satellites. The instrument uses radar to measure backscatter to determine speed and direction of winds over the surface of the oceans. ASCAT observations fields have regular spatial resolutions of 0.25° in longitude and latitude.
The daily wind fields are calculated in near real time with a delay of 48 hours.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Access Oceanographic and Environmental Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/23/2018/wind-in-the-western-indian-ocean-region/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/23/2018/wind-in-the-western-indian-ocean-region/</guid>
      <description>ERDDAP is a web service developed by Bob Simons of NOAA serve a repository of environmental variables. There are over sixty ERDDAP servers providing access to a myriad satellite data and model output relevant to oceanography, meteorology, fisheries and marine mammals, among other areas. You find the dataset in this link https://coastwatch.pfeg.noaa.gov/erddap/metadata/fgdc/xml/. The good thing about ERDDAP is its ability to allow users define the area they interested and then subset data that is within the extent of the defined area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drawing Publication Quality maps with ggplot2 in R</title>
      <link>/10/20/2018/genetic-connectivity-in-western-indian-ocean-region/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/20/2018/genetic-connectivity-in-western-indian-ocean-region/</guid>
      <description>Moving from ARGIS to RFor years, ESRI ArcGIS was a core software for most data processing, spatial analysis and drawing of outputs as map. Honestly the elegant high-resolution figures and maps I produced did not come from ArcMap, but rather from Adobe Illustrator. I was doing all the layout of the maps in ArcMap and then export it as in vector format Encapsulated PostScript. I then imported the .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Expore Current Velocity Measured with  ADCP in R</title>
      <link>/10/18/2018/expore-current-velocity-measured-with-adcp-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/18/2018/expore-current-velocity-measured-with-adcp-in-r/</guid>
      <description>PackagesWe need some packages to process ADCP data. These packages includes
require(oce)require(tidyverse)require(visdat)require(naniar)require(UpSetR)Ingest the ADCPThe LTA dataset was imported into R with read.adp() function from oce package
pemba = read.adp(&amp;quot;./adcp/ADCP_DATA/2007_05/M72-5_OS75011_000000.LTA&amp;quot;)Extract variables containedThe ADCP was collected using the broadband instrument with a frequency of 75KHz making a total of 100 cells spaced at an interval of 16 m making a profile of 1600 m deep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing ADCP Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe Second International Indian Ocean Expedition (IIOE-2) collected various oceanographic data within the coastal water of Tanzania. Among the oceanographic data collected using Agulhas II, is the Acoustic Doppler Current Profiles (ADCP). The measurement was carried out from 4th to 9th November 2017. In this post, I will illustrate how to process the ADCP data with R using oce package developed by Kelley &amp;amp; Richards (2018).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CTD Data in R with oce and tidyverse package</title>
      <link>/10/05/2018/ctd-data-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/05/2018/ctd-data-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-package/</guid>
      <description>Introductionin the previous post, we looked at CTD processing and visualization of profile and section with oce package. We saw the necessary tools needed to import, transform and even plotting oceanographic standard graphics. This post introduce to an ecosystem of packages called tidyverse. The three packages in tidyverse that people use in everyday data analyses include the grammer for graphic ggplot develop by Wickham (2016) for data visualization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing  CTD data with OCE package in R</title>
      <link>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Oceanographers love MATLAB\(^\circledR\) for processing oceanographic data. I have no explanation as to why they love Matlab. I suppose it’s been the de facto standard within the field for a long time, and legacy is a big deal. I have used Matlab for data processing and plotting for several years. With MatLab I implemented a vast amount of tools and rather completed numerical models. Being a self sponsored graduate student at an institution that doesn’t have a subscription, I found sticking to Matlab not only is expensive, but also unsustainable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal Climatology of temperature and salinity in the WIO region from Argo floats </title>
      <link>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionFor years oceanographers have measured temperature and salinity from the surface to the ocean bottom (Foster, 1983). However, our ability to obtain reliable temperature and salinity profiles at fairly resolution both in location and time has been improved through the use of profiling floats from the Argo program (Roemmich et al., 2009; Rosell-Fieschi, 2014; Vilibić &amp;amp; Mihanović, 2013). The Argo program started in the early 2000s with the prime objective of monitoring the upper layer of the world oceans (Rosell-Fieschi, 2014).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear Model with R</title>
      <link>/10/02/2018/modelling-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/02/2018/modelling-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post I’am going to illustrate how to model in R. As Wickham &amp;amp; Grolemund1 put it
The prime goal of modeling is to provide simple low-dimension summary of a dataset.
I am not going to bring a novel science in this post but rather to help you learn the most important tools in R2 that will allow you to model your data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drifter-derived seasonal climatology of Sea surface temperature in the Tropical Indian Ocean</title>
      <link>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</guid>
      <description>The study of sea surface temperature (SST) is one of the cornerstone of oceanography. It has applications not only in physics (Bader &amp;amp; Latif, 2003), chemistry (Corrège, 2006) and the earth’s sciences, but in subjects as diverse as biology and economics. SST plays an important role in our quantitative understanding of coastal habitats and species distribution in our global oceans (Grémillet et al., 2008; Müller-Karger, Walsh, Evans, &amp;amp; Meyers, 1991).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface current in the Tropical Indian Ocean Region from Drifter Observations</title>
      <link>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the previous post I showed how to track the East African Coastal Current using trajectories od drifters. In this post, we dive deeper, focusing on creating grids and fill them with number of drifter the median surface current and present them in form of maps. The goal of this routine is to illustrate how to process drifter data in R using tidyverse and other packages.
Needed PackagesWe need to load some packages into R that are used to process the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The East African Coastal Current captured with satellite-tracked drifter observations</title>
      <link>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</guid>
      <description>My interest to explore the EACC comes from its role in linking the boundary currents north of Madagascar and at the equator. It is long established that the East African Coastal Current flows northward along the coast of Tanzania throughout the year1. However, until now we have a rough sketch of the East african coastal current and its seanoal variations. In this post, I am going to illustrate to you how to process drifter data that capture nicely the pathways of the EACC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface Current in Pemba channel: Drifter Perspective</title>
      <link>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionSurface Currents are driven by global wind systems that are fueled by energy from the sun1. These currents inturn transfer heat from the tropics to the polar regions, influencing local and global climate2. Ocean currents are an important abiotic factor that significantly influences food webs and reproduction of marine organisms and the marine ecosystems that they inhabit3. Many species with limited mobility depend on this “liquid wind” to bring food and nutrients to them and to distribute larvae and reproductive cells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing CTD measurements in R with Oce and tidyverse packages</title>
      <link>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I illustrate how to process ship-based CTD data with oce1 package in R2 enviroment. We saw the power of this package in reading, summarizing and visualizing CTD data. The downside of oce package in my opinion is its strickest nature of relying on R base for data processing and plotting—preventing customization. Therefore, in this post I will illustrate how to tranforming oce dataset format into a tibble—a modern data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing ship-based CTD measurements in Pemba Channel with R</title>
      <link>/09/21/2018/vertical-structure-of-temperature-salinity-and-fluorescence-of-the-pemba-channel-from-ctd-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/21/2018/vertical-structure-of-temperature-salinity-and-fluorescence-of-the-pemba-channel-from-ctd-measurements/</guid>
      <description>This post introduces to simple analysis of CTD data using oce1 package in R2 environment. CTD stands for conductivity, temperature, and depth, and refers to a package of electronic instruments that measure these properties.A CTD device’s primary function is to detect how the conductivity and temperature of the water column changes relative to depth. Conductivity is a measure of how well a solution conducts electricity. Conductivity is directly related to salinity, which is the concentration of salt and other inorganic compounds in seawater.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating MODIS Sea Surface Temperature with Global Drifter Program Observations</title>
      <link>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post, I am going to illustrate routines of how to validate sea surface temperatures from Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) with drifters’ sea surface temperature. Drifters measurements serve as in-situ data against MODIS data. The purpose is to assess closeneness (accuracy) of satellite and in-situ SST. I will check the accuracy of acquired (satellite) and measured (drifter) SST, visualize their relationship and test the significance of the relationship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/</guid>
      <description>Sustainable Oceans, Livelihoods and food Security Through Increased Capacity in Ecosystem research in the Western Indian Ocean*SOLSTICE-WIO is a four-year collaborative project funded by the UK Global Challenges Research Fund (GCRF). Launched in October 2017, it brings together local knowledge and international research expertise to address challenges facing the Western Indian Ocean region in a cost-effective way. SOLSTICE demonstrate its approach to strengthening research capacity through three case studies in Kenya, Tanzania and South Africa show in Figure 1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>