<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tool on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/tool/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tool on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/tool/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Time Series Data in R</title>
      <link>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionShumway and Stoffer (2017) in the book with a title Time series analysis and its applications: with R examples clearly stated that when dealing with any time series analysis the first step you ought to do befure further investigation is careful examination of the recorded data. This means before looking more closely at the particular statistical methods, it is appropriate to plot the recorded data against time. This scrutiny often suggests the method of analysis as well as statistics that will be of use in summarizing the information in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>