<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ggplot2 on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/ggplot2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ggplot2 on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/ggplot2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting Pie and Donut Chart with ggpubr pckage in R</title>
      <link>/04/06/2020/plotting-pie-and-donut-chart-with-ggpubr-pckage-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/04/06/2020/plotting-pie-and-donut-chart-with-ggpubr-pckage-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Once in this blog I explained how to make pie chart and donut plot with ggplot2. In this post, I will extend the topic by introducing ggpubr package, which has nifty function to facilitate a hustle free process of plotting publication quality figures. I will show you how you can use the function from this package to make a pie chart and donut chart with additional function to polish the charts from ggplot2 (Wickham 2016).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barplot with errorbar in ggplot2</title>
      <link>/03/25/2020/barplot-with-errorbar-in-ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/25/2020/barplot-with-errorbar-in-ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionBar plots with error bars are very frequently used plots in sciences to represent the variation in a continuous variable within one or more categorical variables. Error bars give a general idea of how precise a measurement is, or conversely, how far from the reported value the true (error free) value might be. If the value displayed on your barplot is the result of an aggregation (like the mean value of several data points), you may want to display error bars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World map and Map projections</title>
      <link>/01/26/2020/world-map-and-map-projections/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/01/26/2020/world-map-and-map-projections/</guid>
      <description>A map projection is a way to flatten a globe’s surface into a plane in order to make a map. This requires a systematic transformation of the latitudes and longitudes of locations from the surface of the globe into locations on a plane.[1] All projections of a sphere on a plane necessarily distort the surface in some way and to some extent. Depending on the purpose of the map, some distortions are acceptable and others are not; therefore, different map projections exist in order to preserve some properties of the sphere-like body at the expense of other properties.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>