<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Iioe 2 on Masumbuko Semba</title>
    <link>/tags/iioe-2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Iioe 2 on Masumbuko Semba</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/iioe-2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing ADCP Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe Second International Indian Ocean Expedition (IIOE-2) collected variaous oceanographic data within the coastal water of Tanzania. Among the oceanographic data collected using Agulhas II, is the Acoustic Doppler Current Profiles (ADCP). The measurement was carried out from 4th to 9th November 2017.
require(oce)require(ocedata)require(tidyverse)require(lubridate)require(leaflet)require(sf)adp = read.adp(&amp;quot;C:/Users/Semba/Documents/IIOE2/adcp/IIEO2/AGU028002_000000.LTA&amp;quot;)# summary(adp)time = adp[[&amp;quot;time&amp;quot;]]An ADCP (RD Instruments WH-Sentinel 300 kHz) was deployed ~25 km off the coast of Hokkaido (142°39.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface current in the Tropical Indian Ocean Region from Drifter Observations</title>
      <link>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the previous post I showed how to track the East African Coastal Current using trajectories od drifters. In this post, we dive deeper, focusing on creating grids and fill them with number of drifter the median surface current and present them in form of maps. The goal of this routine is to illustrate how to process drifter data in R using tidyverse and other packages.
Needed PackagesWe need to load some packages into R that are used to process the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing CTD measurements in R with Oce and tidyverse packages</title>
      <link>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I illustrate how to process ship-based CTD data with oce1 package in R2 enviroment. We saw the power of this package in reading, summarizing and visualizing CTD data. The downside of oce package in my opinion is its strickest nature of relying on R base for data processing and plotting—preventing customization. Therefore, in this post I will illustrate how to tranforming oce dataset format into a tibble—a modern data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>