<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marine on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/marine/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Marine on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/marine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Python as a tool for oceagraphy and marine sciences</title>
      <link>/07/02/2020/python-as-a-tool-for-oceagraphy-and-marine-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/07/02/2020/python-as-a-tool-for-oceagraphy-and-marine-sciences/</guid>
      <description>During the last couple of decades, Matlab has been the most commonly-used scripting language in physical oceanography (Bengtsson 2018), and it has a large user base in many other fields. However, Python has been gaining ground, often being adopted by former Matlab users as well as by newcomers. Here is a little background to help you understand this shift, and why we advocate using Python from the start.
Python was designed by a computer scientist as a general–purpose scripting language for easy adoption and widespread use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heatmaps in R with ggplot2 and metR packages </title>
      <link>/05/10/2020/heatmaps-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-metr-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/10/2020/heatmaps-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-metr-packages/</guid>
      <description>Heatmaps are powerful data visualization tools broadly widely used with meteorologic and oceanographic data. Heatmaps are excellent at tracking signals that move, like ocean current. These diagrams can be used for many more types of atmospheric features. The concept is to represent a matrix of values as colors where usually is organized by a gradient. This post explains how to create a heatmap of ocean current in R using the geom_tile(), geom_contour_filled from ggplot2 (Wickham 2016) and geom_contour_fill from metR package (Campitelli 2019).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>