<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ADCP on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/adcp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ADCP on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/adcp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Heatmaps in R with ggplot2 and metR packages </title>
      <link>/05/10/2020/heatmaps-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-metr-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/10/2020/heatmaps-in-r-with-ggplot2-and-metr-packages/</guid>
      <description>Heatmaps are powerful data visualization tools broadly widely used with meteorologic and oceanographic data. Heatmaps are excellent at tracking signals that move, like ocean current. These diagrams can be used for many more types of atmospheric features. The concept is to represent a matrix of values as colors where usually is organized by a gradient. This post explains how to create a heatmap of ocean current in R using the geom_tile(), geom_contour_filled from ggplot2 (Wickham 2016) and geom_contour_fill from metR package (Campitelli 2019).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographical coordinates conversion made easy with parzer package in R</title>
      <link>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Geographic coordinates are often in “degrees” but they can also include “minutes” and “seconds”. This gives us a variety of different formats for reporting the coordinates and you’ll see that different groups will use different formats. Computers do not really work well with DMS coordinates and we really prefer the coordinates to be in Decimal Degrees or DD.
This format allows us to perform standard decimal math operations on the coordinates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Expore Current Velocity Measured with  ADCP in R</title>
      <link>/10/18/2018/expore-current-velocity-measured-with-adcp-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/18/2018/expore-current-velocity-measured-with-adcp-in-r/</guid>
      <description>PackagesWe need some packages to process ADCP data. These packages includes
require(oce)require(tidyverse)require(visdat)require(naniar)require(UpSetR)Ingest the ADCPThe LTA dataset was imported into R with read.adp() function from oce package
pemba = read.adp(&amp;quot;./adcp/ADCP_DATA/2007_05/M72-5_OS75011_000000.LTA&amp;quot;)Extract variables containedThe ADCP was collected using the broadband instrument with a frequency of 75KHz making a total of 100 cells spaced at an interval of 16 m making a profile of 1600 m deep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing ADCP Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/15/2018/processing-adcp-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe Second International Indian Ocean Expedition (IIOE-2) collected various oceanographic data within the coastal water of Tanzania. Among the oceanographic data collected using Agulhas II, is the Acoustic Doppler Current Profiles (ADCP). The measurement was carried out from 4th to 9th November 2017. In this post, I will illustrate how to process the ADCP data with R using oce package developed by Kelley &amp;amp; Richards (2018).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>