<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>analysis on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in analysis on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting Pie and Donut Chart with ggpubr pckage in R</title>
      <link>/04/06/2020/plotting-pie-and-donut-chart-with-ggpubr-pckage-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/04/06/2020/plotting-pie-and-donut-chart-with-ggpubr-pckage-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Once in this blog I explained how to make pie chart and donut plot with ggplot2. In this post, I will extend the topic by introducing ggpubr package, which has nifty function to facilitate a hustle free process of plotting publication quality figures. I will show you how you can use the function from this package to make a pie chart and donut chart with additional function to polish the charts from ggplot2 (Wickham 2016).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographical coordinates conversion made easy with parzer package in R</title>
      <link>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Geographic coordinates are often in “degrees” but they can also include “minutes” and “seconds”. This gives us a variety of different formats for reporting the coordinates and you’ll see that different groups will use different formats. Computers do not really work well with DMS coordinates and we really prefer the coordinates to be in Decimal Degrees or DD.
This format allows us to perform standard decimal math operations on the coordinates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model and Project the death toll of coronavirus at Wuhan Province in R</title>
      <link>/02/08/2020/model-and-project-the-death-toll-of-coronavirus-at-wuhan-province-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/08/2020/model-and-project-the-death-toll-of-coronavirus-at-wuhan-province-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe recent contagious 2019-nCoV Wuhan coronavirus outbreak in China has brought shocks and triggered panic among the general population around the world. This noval coronavirus (nCoV) is a new strain that has never been identified in humans before. The risk associated with this virus to human led the World Health Organization (WHO) of United Nations to declare 2019-nCoV as global health emergency.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>