<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Drifter on Masumbuko Semba</title>
    <link>/tags/drifter/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Drifter on Masumbuko Semba</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/drifter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface Current in Pemba channel: Drifter Perspective</title>
      <link>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionSurface Currents are driven by global wind systems that are fueled by energy from the sun1. These currents inturn transfer heat from the tropics to the polar regions, influencing local and global climate2. Ocean currents are an important abiotic factor that significantly influences food webs and reproduction of marine organisms and the marine ecosystems that they inhabit3. Many species with limited mobility depend on this “liquid wind” to bring food and nutrients to them and to distribute larvae and reproductive cells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating MODIS Sea Surface Temperature with Global Drifter Program Observations</title>
      <link>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post, I am going to illustrate routines of how to validate sea surface temperatures from Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) with drifters’ sea surface temperature. Drifters measurements serve as in-situ data against MODIS data. The purpose is to assess closeneness (accuracy) of satellite and in-situ SST. I will check the accuracy of acquired (satellite) and measured (drifter) SST, visualize their relationship and test the significance of the relationship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>