<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bathymetry on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/bathymetry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bathymetry on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/bathymetry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lake Victoria Bathymetry</title>
      <link>/04/24/2020/lake-victoria-bathymetry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/04/24/2020/lake-victoria-bathymetry/</guid>
      <description>I was looking for bathymetry dataset for Lake Victoria online and I came across this link. It stores several products of the bathymetry data of the Lake Victoria. Among them products is the gridded TIFF file. This dataset was created by a team from Harvard University in 2017 (Hamilton et al. 2016). They used over 4.2 million points collected over 100-years of surveys.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographical coordinates conversion made easy with parzer package in R</title>
      <link>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Geographic coordinates are often in “degrees” but they can also include “minutes” and “seconds”. This gives us a variety of different formats for reporting the coordinates and you’ll see that different groups will use different formats. Computers do not really work well with DMS coordinates and we really prefer the coordinates to be in Decimal Degrees or DD.
This format allows us to perform standard decimal math operations on the coordinates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plotting the Spatial distribution of Chlorophyll in Mafia Channel from MODIS</title>
      <link>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</guid>
      <description>Making graphics and maps is one of the important skills for oceanographers and marine scientists. Maps are often used by scientists to locate areas of interest—where the study being presented was conducted. Thus ability to make maps that convey the message in a simple manner form an important first impression for readers. Despite this, software tools for producing high-quality maps are non-trivial to use.
In this post I illustrate how some key lines of code for access, download and map the spatial distribution of chlorophyll-a concentration within the Rufiji-Mafia Channel using a combination of packages in the R environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the bathymetry of Coastal Tanzania from ETOPO1 with oce package in R</title>
      <link>/02/14/2019/mapping-the-bathmetry-of-coastal-tanzania-from-etopo1-with-oce-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/14/2019/mapping-the-bathmetry-of-coastal-tanzania-from-etopo1-with-oce-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, we explore the power of oce package in mapping oceanographic data. In this post we will continue that theme and dive to process topographic data and map the bathymetry. We will grab ETOPO1 dataset— a 1 arc-minute global relief model that integrates land topography and ocean bathymetry. We will process the data and then use different ways to visualize the bathymetric information. There is no much statistics or modelling in this post, but the post focus on letting you know how to process the ascii (.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>