<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>chlorophyll on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/chlorophyll/</link>
    <description>Recent content in chlorophyll on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/chlorophyll/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A simple Principal Component Analysis (PCA) in R </title>
      <link>/05/13/2020/simple-pca-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/13/2020/simple-pca-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Principal Component Analysis (PCA)Principal Component Analysis (PCA) is widely used to explore data. This technique allows you visualize and understand how variables in the dataset varies. Therefore, PCA is particularly helpful where the dataset contain many variables.This is a method of unsupervised learning that allows you to better understand the variability in the data set and how different variables are related.
The Components in PCA are the underlying structure in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plotting the Spatial distribution of Chlorophyll in Mafia Channel from MODIS</title>
      <link>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</guid>
      <description>Making graphics and maps is one of the important skills for oceanographers and marine scientists. Maps are often used by scientists to locate areas of interest—where the study being presented was conducted. Thus ability to make maps that convey the message in a simple manner form an important first impression for readers. Despite this, software tools for producing high-quality maps are non-trivial to use.
In this post I illustrate how some key lines of code for access, download and map the spatial distribution of chlorophyll-a concentration within the Rufiji-Mafia Channel using a combination of packages in the R environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting chlorophyll value in the Pemba channel with the prophet package in R</title>
      <link>/05/31/2019/forecasting-chlorophyll-value-in-the-pemba-channel-with-the-prophet-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/31/2019/forecasting-chlorophyll-value-in-the-pemba-channel-with-the-prophet-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>introductionTime series analysis comprises methods for predicting the future based on the historical in order to extract meaningful statistics and other characteristics of the data. In other words, time series forecasting is the use of a model to predict future values based on previously observed values. Time series are widely used for non-stationary data, like economic, weather, stock price, and retail sales in this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primary Production, chlorophyll-concentration and Sea surface temperature in Tanzania waters</title>
      <link>/02/15/2019/primary-production-chlorophyll-concentration-and-sea-surface-temperature-in-tanzania-waters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/15/2019/primary-production-chlorophyll-concentration-and-sea-surface-temperature-in-tanzania-waters/</guid>
      <description>Introductionrequire(tidyverse)require(oce)require(highcharter)require(lubridate)files = dir(&amp;quot;extracted/&amp;quot;, pattern = &amp;quot;chl_&amp;quot;, full.names = TRUE)chlorophyll-aChlorophyll-a is certainly the most commonly derived parameter in water quality mainly because of its use in determining the trophic status of waters.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>