<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tanzania on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/tanzania/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tanzania on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/tanzania/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive map with leaflet</title>
      <link>/03/17/2019/interactive-map-with-leaflet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/17/2019/interactive-map-with-leaflet/</guid>
      <description>This post aim to train you how to make an interactive in R. We are going to focus on some poular packages for these task, many are part onf an tidyverse ecosystem (Wickham 2017) with addition of leaflet(Cheng, Karambelkar, and Xie 2018) package. To work with these post you need to have version 3.4 and above of R(R Core Team 2018) installed in your machine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Time Series Data in R</title>
      <link>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/22/2019/exploring-time-series-data-in-r/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionShumway and Stoffer (2017) in the book with a title Time series analysis and its applications: with R examples clearly stated that when dealing with any time series analysis the first step you ought to do befure further investigation is careful examination of the recorded data. This means before looking more closely at the particular statistical methods, it is appropriate to plot the recorded data against time. This scrutiny often suggests the method of analysis as well as statistics that will be of use in summarizing the information in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time series analysis in R</title>
      <link>/02/20/2019/time-series-analysis-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/20/2019/time-series-analysis-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Any quantitative value measured over regular time intervals makes a Time Series. Time-series analysis aims to investigate the temporal behavior of a variable \(X_{t}\). Examples include the investigation of long-term records of sea surface temperature, sea-level fluctuations, millennium-scale variations in the atmosphere-ocean system, the eff ect of the El-Niño/Southern Oscillation on tropical rainfall and sedimentation (Trauth 2015). R has extensive facilities for analyzing time series data. These packages provides various tools with which to detect these temporal patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the bathymetry of Coastal Tanzania from ETOPO1 with oce package in R</title>
      <link>/02/14/2019/mapping-the-bathmetry-of-coastal-tanzania-from-etopo1-with-oce-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/14/2019/mapping-the-bathmetry-of-coastal-tanzania-from-etopo1-with-oce-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, we explore the power of oce package in mapping oceanographic data. In this post we will continue that theme and dive to process topographic data and map the bathymetry. We will grab ETOPO1 dataset— a 1 arc-minute global relief model that integrates land topography and ocean bathymetry. We will process the data and then use different ways to visualize the bathymetric information. There is no much statistics or modelling in this post, but the post focus on letting you know how to process the ascii (.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing classical methods for estimating the mixed layer depth along the transect off Kimbiji, Tanzania</title>
      <link>/02/09/2019/comparing-classical-methods-for-estimating-the-mixed-layer-depth-along-the-transect-off-kimbiji-tanzania/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/09/2019/comparing-classical-methods-for-estimating-the-mixed-layer-depth-along-the-transect-off-kimbiji-tanzania/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionUpper Ocean is characterized for a quasi-homogeneous layer where temperature, salinity and density almost constant with increasing depth (Costoya et al. 2014). This homogeneity layer is caused by turbulent vertical mixing that is driven by heat loss from the ocean to the atmosphere, as well as by wind stress (Stranne et al. 2018). The deepest layer affected by this turbulent mixing is called mixed layer depth (MLD), which marks the width of the upper ocean that interacts with the atmosphere (Kelley 2018).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Access and Process Quikscat Wind speed and direction with R</title>
      <link>/10/27/2018/access-and-process-quikscat-wind-speed-and-direction-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/27/2018/access-and-process-quikscat-wind-speed-and-direction-with-r/</guid>
      <description>quikscatIn his An Introduction to the Near–Real–Time QuikSCAT Data, Hoffman (2005) described the primary mission of the SeaWinds instrument on the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Quick Scatterometer (QuikSCAT ) satellite was to retrieve the surface vector wind over the global ocean (Lungu 2001).
QuikSCAT has provided an extremely accurate and extraordinarily comprehensive view of the surface wind over the global ocean since July 1999 (Chelton et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing Satellite Wind Speed Data with R</title>
      <link>/10/25/2018/processing-satellite-wind-speed-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/25/2018/processing-satellite-wind-speed-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>The Advanced Scatterometer (ASCAT) winds products are processed by NOAA/NESDIS utilizing measurements from the scatterometer instrument aboard the EUMETSAT Metop satellites. The instrument uses radar to measure backscatter to determine speed and direction of winds over the surface of the oceans. ASCAT observations fields have regular spatial resolutions of 0.25° in longitude and latitude.
The daily wind fields are calculated in near real time with a delay of 48 hours.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing  CTD data with OCE package in R</title>
      <link>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/04/2018/processing-ctd-data-with-oce-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Oceanographers love MATLAB\(^\circledR\) for processing oceanographic data. I have no explanation as to why they love Matlab. I suppose it’s been the de facto standard within the field for a long time, and legacy is a big deal. I have used Matlab for data processing and plotting for several years. With MatLab I implemented a vast amount of tools and rather completed numerical models. Being a self sponsored graduate student at an institution that doesn’t have a subscription, I found sticking to Matlab not only is expensive, but also unsustainable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface current in the Tropical Indian Ocean Region from Drifter Observations</title>
      <link>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the previous post I showed how to track the East African Coastal Current using trajectories od drifters. In this post, we dive deeper, focusing on creating grids and fill them with number of drifter the median surface current and present them in form of maps. The goal of this routine is to illustrate how to process drifter data in R using tidyverse and other packages.
Needed PackagesWe need to load some packages into R that are used to process the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing CTD measurements in R with Oce and tidyverse packages</title>
      <link>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I illustrate how to process ship-based CTD data with oce1 package in R2 enviroment. We saw the power of this package in reading, summarizing and visualizing CTD data. The downside of oce package in my opinion is its strickest nature of relying on R base for data processing and plotting—preventing customization. Therefore, in this post I will illustrate how to tranforming oce dataset format into a tibble—a modern data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>