<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pemba Channel on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/pemba-channel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pemba Channel on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/pemba-channel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>plotting the Spatial distribution of Chlorophyll in Mafia Channel from MODIS</title>
      <link>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/12/01/2019/plotting-the-spatial-distribution-of-chlorophyll-from-modis/</guid>
      <description>Making graphics and maps is one of the important skills for oceanographers and marine scientists. Maps are often used by scientists to locate areas of interest—where the study being presented was conducted. Thus ability to make maps that convey the message in a simple manner form an important first impression for readers. Despite this, software tools for producing high-quality maps are non-trivial to use.
In this post I illustrate how some key lines of code for access, download and map the spatial distribution of chlorophyll-a concentration within the Rufiji-Mafia Channel using a combination of packages in the R environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting chlorophyll value in the Pemba channel with the prophet package in R</title>
      <link>/05/31/2019/forecasting-chlorophyll-value-in-the-pemba-channel-with-the-prophet-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/31/2019/forecasting-chlorophyll-value-in-the-pemba-channel-with-the-prophet-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>introductionTime series analysis comprises methods for predicting the future based on the historical in order to extract meaningful statistics and other characteristics of the data. In other words, time series forecasting is the use of a model to predict future values based on previously observed values. Time series are widely used for non-stationary data, like economic, weather, stock price, and retail sales in this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Global Climatological Annual precipitation with ggplot and metR package in R</title>
      <link>/05/07/2019/climatological-monthly-variation-of-precipitation-in-the-pemba-channel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/05/07/2019/climatological-monthly-variation-of-precipitation-in-the-pemba-channel/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionI recently came across a map showing the climatological annual distribution of rainfall shown in figure 1. I was fascinated with the visual appeal of this map. The map clearly convey the message with clarity, simplicity and visual appeal, which spark my thinking and paused for a moment to figure out how could I make a similar plot like figure 1, which was made in MATLAB in R?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interactive map with leaflet</title>
      <link>/03/17/2019/interactive-map-with-leaflet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/03/17/2019/interactive-map-with-leaflet/</guid>
      <description>This post aim to train you how to make an interactive in R. We are going to focus on some poular packages for these task, many are part onf an tidyverse ecosystem (Wickham 2017) with addition of leaflet(Cheng, Karambelkar, and Xie 2018) package. To work with these post you need to have version 3.4 and above of R(R Core Team 2018) installed in your machine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the bathymetry of Coastal Tanzania from ETOPO1 with oce package in R</title>
      <link>/02/14/2019/mapping-the-bathmetry-of-coastal-tanzania-from-etopo1-with-oce-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/14/2019/mapping-the-bathmetry-of-coastal-tanzania-from-etopo1-with-oce-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, we explore the power of oce package in mapping oceanographic data. In this post we will continue that theme and dive to process topographic data and map the bathymetry. We will grab ETOPO1 dataset— a 1 arc-minute global relief model that integrates land topography and ocean bathymetry. We will process the data and then use different ways to visualize the bathymetric information. There is no much statistics or modelling in this post, but the post focus on letting you know how to process the ascii (.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drawing Publication Quality maps with ggplot2 in R</title>
      <link>/10/20/2018/genetic-connectivity-in-western-indian-ocean-region/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/20/2018/genetic-connectivity-in-western-indian-ocean-region/</guid>
      <description>Moving from ARGIS to RFor years, ESRI ArcGIS was a core software for most data processing, spatial analysis and drawing of outputs as map. Honestly the elegant high-resolution figures and maps I produced did not come from ArcMap, but rather from Adobe Illustrator. I was doing all the layout of the maps in ArcMap and then export it as in vector format Encapsulated PostScript. I then imported the .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drifter-derived seasonal climatology of Sea surface temperature in the Tropical Indian Ocean</title>
      <link>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/30/2018/sea-surface-temperature-from-drifter/</guid>
      <description>The study of sea surface temperature (SST) is one of the cornerstone of oceanography. It has applications not only in physics (Bader &amp;amp; Latif, 2003), chemistry (Corrège, 2006) and the earth’s sciences, but in subjects as diverse as biology and economics. SST plays an important role in our quantitative understanding of coastal habitats and species distribution in our global oceans (Grémillet et al., 2008; Müller-Karger, Walsh, Evans, &amp;amp; Meyers, 1991).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface current in the Tropical Indian Ocean Region from Drifter Observations</title>
      <link>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/28/2018/surface-current-from-drifters/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn the previous post I showed how to track the East African Coastal Current using trajectories od drifters. In this post, we dive deeper, focusing on creating grids and fill them with number of drifter the median surface current and present them in form of maps. The goal of this routine is to illustrate how to process drifter data in R using tidyverse and other packages.
Needed PackagesWe need to load some packages into R that are used to process the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The East African Coastal Current captured with satellite-tracked drifter observations</title>
      <link>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/26/2018/chase-the-east-african-coastal-current-with-satellite-tracked-drifter-observations/</guid>
      <description>My interest to explore the EACC comes from its role in linking the boundary currents north of Madagascar and at the equator. It is long established that the East African Coastal Current flows northward along the coast of Tanzania throughout the year1. However, until now we have a rough sketch of the East african coastal current and its seanoal variations. In this post, I am going to illustrate to you how to process drifter data that capture nicely the pathways of the EACC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface Current in Pemba channel: Drifter Perspective</title>
      <link>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/24/2018/surface-current-in-pemba-channel-drifter-perspective/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionSurface Currents are driven by global wind systems that are fueled by energy from the sun1. These currents inturn transfer heat from the tropics to the polar regions, influencing local and global climate2. Ocean currents are an important abiotic factor that significantly influences food webs and reproduction of marine organisms and the marine ecosystems that they inhabit3. Many species with limited mobility depend on this “liquid wind” to bring food and nutrients to them and to distribute larvae and reproductive cells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processing CTD measurements in R with Oce and tidyverse packages</title>
      <link>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/22/2018/processing-ctd-measurements-in-r-with-oce-and-tidyverse-packages/</guid>
      <description>In the previous post, I illustrate how to process ship-based CTD data with oce1 package in R2 enviroment. We saw the power of this package in reading, summarizing and visualizing CTD data. The downside of oce package in my opinion is its strickest nature of relying on R base for data processing and plotting—preventing customization. Therefore, in this post I will illustrate how to tranforming oce dataset format into a tibble—a modern data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Validating MODIS Sea Surface Temperature with Global Drifter Program Observations</title>
      <link>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/20/2018/validating-modis-sea-surface-temperature-with-global-drifter-program-observations/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionIn this post, I am going to illustrate routines of how to validate sea surface temperatures from Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) with drifters’ sea surface temperature. Drifters measurements serve as in-situ data against MODIS data. The purpose is to assess closeneness (accuracy) of satellite and in-situ SST. I will check the accuracy of acquired (satellite) and measured (drifter) SST, visualize their relationship and test the significance of the relationship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting and Processing Satellite Data made easier in R</title>
      <link>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/09/18/2018/get-satellite-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: A Brief OverviewThe amount of data being generated by satellites has soared in recent years. The proliferation of remote sensing data can be explained by recent advancements in satellite technologies. However, according to Febvre1, this advancement set another challenge of handling and processing pentabyte of data satellite generates. Thanks to ERDDAP, for being in front-line to overcome this challenge. We can obtain satellite data within the geographical extent of the area we are interested.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>