<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/climate/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Climate on Masumbuko Semba&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/climate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographical coordinates conversion made easy with parzer package in R</title>
      <link>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/25/2020/geographical-coordinates-conversion-made-easy-with-parzer-package-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Geographic coordinates are often in “degrees” but they can also include “minutes” and “seconds”. This gives us a variety of different formats for reporting the coordinates and you’ll see that different groups will use different formats. Computers do not really work well with DMS coordinates and we really prefer the coordinates to be in Decimal Degrees or DD.
his format allows us to perform standard decimal math operations on the coordinates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Mixed Layer Depth with Optimal Linear fitting method.</title>
      <link>/02/08/2019/different-approaches-of-detecting-mixed-layer-depth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/02/08/2019/different-approaches-of-detecting-mixed-layer-depth/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe mixed layer is a thin layer with constant temperature and salinity from the surface down to a depth where the values differ from those at the surface (Boyer Montégut et al. 2004). Wind blowing on the ocean stirs the upper layers leading to a thin mixed layer (Stewart 2008). The resulting surface mixed layer is important for local primary production, climate and ocean circulation (Kelley 2018). Although the mixed layer is an important oceanographic parameter, there different approaches that are used and each method depends on the scientific application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal Climatology of temperature and salinity in the WIO region from Argo floats </title>
      <link>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/10/03/2018/seasonal-climatology-of-temperature-and-salinity-in-the-wio-region-from-argo-floats/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionFor years oceanographers have measured temperature and salinity from the surface to the ocean bottom (Foster, 1983). However, our ability to obtain reliable temperature and salinity profiles at fairly resolution both in location and time has been improved through the use of profiling floats from the Argo program (Roemmich et al., 2009; Rosell-Fieschi, 2014; Vilibić &amp;amp; Mihanović, 2013). The Argo program started in the early 2000s with the prime objective of monitoring the upper layer of the world oceans (Rosell-Fieschi, 2014).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>